So in this section we're going to talk about
like what is programming and we're going to do
so by reviewing things like Python and C. And
the reason we take a look at this is that when
we write Python or C that code has to execute
eventually in machine language. So in the end
any program that we can write must also be
representable in machine language. So if we
look at patterns in high level programming, we
need to be able to replicate those patterns in
machine language. So I'm going to take you back in
time to 2008 when I first was teaching the course
that would become Python for Everybody on campus
at the University of Michigan. This was chapter 1,
slide 19. So this is for people who'd never seen
a computer, never I mean never you programmed a
computer, never didn't know what programming was.
And I introduced computer architecture in slide
19. And why was that? Well, my goal at that point
was to teach people that to become a programmer,
you kind of move into the machine. Your code
moves into the machine and it provides the
instructions to the central processing unit.
And so your goal to becoming a programmer is
to be able to provide those instructions so
you can have the overall machine do the thing
that you want to do. Now the key is those
instructions and I said this in chapter 1
slide 19 those instructions are zeros and
ones and they are what is called machine
language and those instructions are moved from
the main memory to the central processing unit.
using wires. And that was like the first half hour
of the first day of programming. And now some of
you have been with me for some time. And now we're
at the point where we're going to understand what
exactly a central processing unit is. Okay. So
let me show you some of the artifacts that I used
when teaching that class. So let's start with the
central processor. I've shown you this AMD central
processor before. We now know how to build this
chip. We understand that instructions will come
into these wires, right? So like if there is uh
eight of them, we can represent those eight wires
as a hexadecimal digit because we just learned
how to do hexadecimal. Now the place that these
instructions come from in that same picture is
the memory. And so again, you've got wires and
four of these wires equals one hexadecimal digit,
right? Lots of wires. We got chips that store,
but we've also learned how to build uh latches
that are ways to store memory electronically
and then retrieve that memory. But then we have
to come up with a way to connect these things
together. And that's what's called a motherboard,
right? And so the CPU plugs in to the Oops,
here we go. CPU plugs into the CPU slot. The
memory plugs into a memory slot. And there are
wires on this motherboard that are laid out to
pull so that the CPU can ask the memory for some
data instructions. And it comes here and it and we
also load and store the, you know, the the things
we're going to compute from the memory as well.
And so if you look at this, it's got like big and
small wires. It's mostly wires with these little
through holes that are soldered into the wires.
Um you can see kind of big things. They're like
roads and lakes, but these wires go. And so again,
I'm going to sorry, I'm going to get all stuck
on this. Four of these little pins, I mean,
eight of these little pins are two hex digits. So
we can represent all these pins perhaps with a big
long hex string. And that's kind of why we're so
obsessed with hexadecimal. I'm clearly obsessed
with hexadecimal. And the other thing that I
showed students in the very beginning was this
disc drive. Now, modern computers don't have disc
drives that actually have any physical spinning.
But basically, this was magnetic material and
this head would go in and out. I think this is now
broken, but the head would go in and out and the
data would be stored on cylinders up and down. And
so this head would move in and out. And if you're
old enough, you would remember your computer while
you're reading disc, it would go uh uh uh grunt
grunt grunt grunt grunt. Well, that grunt is this
stuff moving back and forth. And it seems as
though I have had this over 10 years and I've
scratched it and I've broken it. But you get the
idea that this was long-term storage and you could
store a lot more data than you can in RAM. The
the the memory is fast and efficient but limited
and disc drives are much larger in terms of the
amount of data they can store. And once stored,
it stays there and doesn't require power. Now,
the other thing that I showed my students,
the other thing that I showed my students is
something a little bit more modern, which is a
little more like what's in your cell phone, etc.
And this is a Raspberry Pi. And what's happened
is as they can manufacture more and more stuff
on a single chip, you can get to what's called a
single chip computer. So, in this has got the CPU,
it's got some long-term storage, it's got the RAM,
etc., etc. And so, this is got everything
in it because it's really just electronic
stuff. And as the manufacturing capability got
better and better, this is an ARM processor,
which we'll talk about later, and some RAM, etc.
And this is one of the early Raspberry Pies.
So 15 years ago, it was a little easier to show
computer architecture by showing the components
that made up computer architecture. It's not
just a picture. It was physical devices that
implemented the computer architecture. The
instructions were stored in the memory. The
whole program when the computer was off was
stored on the hard drive, loaded into memory,
etc. And the motherboard connected all of these
pieces together. So the next thing that I describe
to my students in SI502 Python for everybody
is how we construct programs and these are the
essential things like a recipe or an installation
instructions. A program is a sequence of steps to
be done in order like the Macarena. Some steps
are conditional. They may be skipped and another
way you have a group of steps that may want to be
repeated. And the fourth way is like functions. we
store and retrieve a set of steps. We are going to
cover the first three of these in machine language
to sort of prove to you that machine language can
do exactly what high level languages do just with
a different syntax and a different level of detail
that you you're limited with what you can do in
machine language. Some people feel like machine
language limitations is kind of wonderful until
you start writing really complex programs. Okay,
but the first view of machine language that you're
going like, "Wow, this is kind of nice. Maybe
I should have learned this at the beginning."
So now into some Python, we have first sequential
steps. You just write lines of code one after the
other. And like x= 2, print x, that prints out
the two, x= x + 2, we just added to two to x,
and then print x. So what next? What next? the CPU
through its program counter is advancing through
the instructions and doing whatever it is until
it executes a halt instruction which means okay
we're now done you the programmer have said we're
done there's also conditional steps like you know
x= 5 if x is less than 10 print smaller if x
is greater than 20 print bigger or print Finis
and so this is things like the print smaller is
going to run but the print bigger is not going to
run and we represent these on the left hand side
with a flowchart. And so I have been teaching with
flowcharts. A lot of people think flowcharts are
uncool, but in the next couple of lectures you're
going to appreciate flowcharts because in a sense
we are guiding the what next bit to either do
something or skip something. And so logically
they're beautiful. The the code in Python is
beautiful. There are these blocks. they either
run or don't run. But really what we're doing
at a lower level is we're manipulating where the
computer is picking its next instruction from.
And this all will come together in a little
bit. And it gets even more complex when we do
repeated steps, right? Where we have an iteration
variable, we have a loop. So n equals 5. Well,
n greater than zero. That's a top- tested loop
with a question mark. And if n is still greater
than zero, we run the body of the loop, print
it, and then subtract one from it. And now then
we know that we go back up to the top of the
loop. And the first thing we do at the top of
the loop is test it again. Is n as changed. Is
n still greater than zero? I mean, if it's not
greater than zero, we skip and finish and print
blast off. And if it is still greater than zero,
we run the iteration again and again. You of
course can create infinite loops with this
if you don't change the iteration variable
each time through the loop. And that brings
us to variables. So a variable is a place in
memory where a programmer can store data and
then later retrieve it using a variable name
like x= 12.2 y= 14 and then x= 100 replaces it.
Now, for some of you who've took my Django course,
I finally admit that X is not just a drawer that's
got a label on it. X is a pointer to an object.
So, X= 12.2 means 12.2 is an object and X refers
to that object. When we say X= 100, there's
another object called 100 and X has changed to
point to that. So if you've taken my CC class
then you realize that with pointers that this
is exactly true. A a variable is a place where
you can put one and exactly one value and when
you reassign it that value is replaced just like
this picture up next. We're going to learn about
how variables work in machine language. And it
will probably come as no surprise to you that
they work exactly like how C thinks about them
because C is one of the lowest level programming
languages which is just a tiny step above machine
language. And so instead of being Python with all
its object orientation eventually that whole
Python object orientation turns into machine
language but variables don't exactly work like
this slide tells us. But in machine language,
this slide is exactly correct. So let's
get to that now. [Music] [Applause] [Music]